In 452 AD, Attila the Hun led a huge army
of allied Germanic and Asiatic warriors into
northern Italy. Legend has it that Attila, who the
Romans termed Flagellum Dei, ‘the scourge of god’,
was only stopped when Pope Leo I met the warlord
and convinced him to leave Italy. Unlike Alaric
the Goth in 410 AD or the Vandal King Gaiseric in
455 AD, Attila never sacked the city of Rome. So
why is he remembered today as the most fearsome of
the barbarian warlords who destroyed the Western
Roman Empire? This is the story of Attila
the Hun, ‘the scourge of god’.
The man known to history as Attila the Hun
was born early in the fifth century AD,
perhaps around the year 406 AD. There is no
tangible evidence about his earliest years
to establish when he was born and historians
have simply extrapolated his date of birth
from the fact that, he was seemingly in his
thirties when he first came to prominence
in the mid-430s AD. Similarly, his place of
birth is unclear, though given what we know
about the westward movement of the Huns in
the first years of the fifth century, he was
more than likely born somewhere around western
Ukraine, Moldova or northern Romania.
There is an equal lack of certainty when it
comes to Attila’s family background. His father
was a prominent Hun warlord who was variously
referred to as Mundzuk, Mundzucus and Mundiucus
by Greek and Roman scholars of the fifth and sixth
centuries AD. There is no clear indication of who
Attila’s mother was. Prominent warlords amongst
the Huns practiced polygamy and Attila could have
been born to a concubine or one of several wives
of Mundzuk. We do know that he had a brother named
Bleda, who became an important figure in events
later in Attila’s life. His father was a brother
of the Hun leaders, Rugila and Octar, and Attila
was consequently born into the ruling kinship
group amongst the Huns at the start of the fifth
century AD. Despite his origin amongst the Huns,
a people who had migrated across Eurasia from the
Asian Steppe in the centuries prior to his birth,
there is a strong argument that Attila’s name
is Germanic. Atta roughly means ‘father’ in
East Germanic dialects like Gothic and the ila
suffix means ‘little’. Thus, Attila would mean
‘little father’ if the name was Germanic. Cultural
osmosis of the kind that would lead a warlord like
Mundzuk amongst the Asiatic Huns to call his
son by a Germanic name, was commonplace in
the late Roman imperial period. An alternative
theory holds that the name comes from a Turkic
dialect and means ‘great ocean’ or ‘old sea’.
Reconstructing the life of Attila the Hun poses
some difficulties. Firstly, there is the question
of bias in the sources. The Huns were not a
literate people and they did not have chroniclers
who could write accounts of their actions from
their perspective. Therefore, we are primarily
reliant on Roman and Greek historians for
information on Attila and the Huns. These accounts
were far from neutral. For about thirty years in
the middle of the fifth century AD, the Huns were
the gravest threat to the Roman Empire and Attila
in particular brought devastation to parts of
both the Balkans and Western Europe. Accordingly,
the Greco-Roman historians who charted the
actions of Attila would have described his deeds
in a hostile manner. The foremost contemporary
account of their campaigns was written by Priscus,
a Greek historian from near Constantinople, who
wrote a history of the Eastern Roman Empire.
Priscus was a diplomat who actually visited
Attila’s court in 447 AD. His work has only
survived in a fragmentary format, but it was used
by the sixth-century historian Jordanes in his
The Origins and Deeds of the Goths, a major work
on the various Germanic and Asiatic tribes that
repeatedly attacked the Roman Empire from the
third century AD onwards. For the Western Roman
Empire, Prosper of Aquitaine’s Gallic Chronicle is
a key source of information as Prosper also lived
through Attila’s attacks on the empire. There
are also some fragments of information in the
works like the chronicle of Hydatius of Aquae
Flaviae, a churchman from Gaul, while there
are passing references to Attila and the Huns in
the surviving letters of Sidonius Apollinaris,
a Gallo-Roman aristocrat, who grew up against
the backdrop of Attila’s campaigns and remembered
them in later life. These sources are of varying
quality and reliability, and are biased, but they
provide enough information to at least partially
reconstruct the events of Attila’s life.
The one thing that these sources don’t tell us,
is where the Huns came from. Roman and Greek
historians and scholars had a good idea of the
geography of places like Poland and the lands
north of the Black Sea stretching east along
the Pontic-Caspian Sea, but beyond that they
were largely unclear about the geography and
demography of places further afield. They had
no real knowledge of the place the Huns came from.
This was the Asian Steppe, a vast flatland on the
northern side of the Himalayan Mountains, a part
of the world from which other tribal groups like
the Turks and Mongols would later emerge, to
conquer much of Eurasia. The Huns were similar
to these later groups. Before they ever came to
Europe, they had possibly been raiding into China
for centuries and are quite possibly synonymous
with the nomadic raiders which the Chinese knew as
the Hsiung-Nu or Xiongnu. Later the Huns started
to move westwards as part of a vast migration of
Germanic and Asiatic people towards the Roman
Empire, which was occurring as people were
pulled towards Rome’s borders by the possibility
of rich plunder and also pushed westwards from
the Asian and Pontic-Caspian Steppes by climate
change that was impacting on their traditional
pastoral subsistence. By the middle of the
fourth century AD, the Huns began migrating
over the Ural Mountains and towards the River
Volga. As they advanced further westwards they
pushed other Germanic and Asiatic groups onwards
towards Rome’s borders. Hence, the Huns were
impacting on the Roman Empire before the Romans
were ever aware of who they even were.
The Roman Empire was ripe for plundering by the
time the Huns began to descend into what is now
Ukraine and the Carpathian Basin at the very end
of the fourth century and the start of the fifth.
The empire had been divided for administrative
purposes into an eastern and western half in the
late third century. A hundred years later
the empire splintered fully into a Western
Roman Empire and Eastern Roman Empire in 395
AD. Within a few years the government in the
east tried to rid themselves of the invading
Goths, who had largely taken over the Balkans,
by encouraging them to attack the Western
Roman Empire. So it was, that in 410 AD,
Alaric the Goth sacked the city of Rome. The
very same year, the Roman legions strategically
withdrew from Britain, while over the next twenty
years groups like the Franks, Alemanni and Vandals
conquered large parts of Gaul, Hispania and
even North Africa. This was the situation
which prevailed as the Huns began to move into
Central Europe in the early fifth century AD.
Although Attila is by far the best attested
ruler of the Huns, as Greek and Roman writers
like Priscus and Jordanes wrote extensively about
him, we also know a little about their leadership
as Attila was growing up. Around the time of
his birth, the Huns were led by a warlord named
Uldin. He is the first Hunnic leader mentioned by
name in the Greek and Roman histories of the era.
While the Goths were raiding through the
Balkans and then into Italy in the mid-400s,
Uldin evidently led his men into Dacia, modern-day
Romania, and began conquering parts of that
province and exacting tribute from the local Roman
authorities in order to not raid further south or
west. As far away as Bethlehem in the Levant,
St Jerome wrote of a new people he had heard
of who “had poured forth from the distant Sea of
Azov,” and who were “flying hither and thither on
their swift steeds … filling the whole world with
bloodshed and panic.” Uldin was succeeded not long
afterwards, by a Hun warlord named Charaton in
the early 410s. By then, the Huns had begun moving
into the Carpathian Basin and were emerging as the
chief adversary of the Eastern Roman Empire in the
Balkans. We don’t know a lot about their internal
politics at this early stage and it is unclear if
either Uldin or Charaton were related to Attila
in any way.
Attila’s early life can only be guessed
at. The Huns were illiterate and there was
no formal schooling amongst them in the way we
understand it today. Instead, the education of
a warlord’s son like Attila would have been in
teaching him to ride a horse and to fight from
childhood. When he reached his teenage years, he
was quasi-royalty within the leadership of the
Huns. Jordanes mentions that Mundzuk, Attila’s
father, was the brother of Octar and Rugila.
They were the joint-rulers of the Huns in the 420s
AD. It is possible that they had divided the Hun
confederacy between them and Octar led the Western
Huns, while Rugila was in charge of their eastern
lands, launching raids south against the Eastern
Roman Empire. Jordanes left behind a description
of Attila in his adult years, though there may
have been some artistic licence in terms of how
he described an individual whom he had never
met. He stated that “He had an arrogant walk,
and he rolled his eyes as he looked about. The
power of that haughty spirit showed through
in every movement of his body. He certainly
loved war, yet he was restrained, lenient to
those to whom he gave his protection, gracious to
supplicants and keen of judgement. He was short,
with a barrel chest and a large head. He had small
eyes and a sparse beard flecked with grey. His
ancestry was plainly evident in his flat nose and
swarthy complexion.” This was the Hun who would
become known as “the scourge of god.”
Attila’s rise to power along with his brother
Bleda occurred around 434 AD. Their succession
as leaders of the Hun confederacy followed from
the death of their uncle, Rugila. It’s not clear
why Attila and Bleda succeeded to the leadership,
as they did have another surviving uncle named
Oebarsius, who was alive in the late 440s AD.
It seems likely that Attila and Bleda’s father,
Mundzuk, was already dead before Rugila died.
The succession of Attila and Bleda as joint rulers
of the Huns echoed the earlier arrangement between
Octar and Rugila and they may have had different
spheres of influence in the Balkans. At the
time that they succeeded, the Huns were living
relatively peacefully in the Carpathian Basin.
Rugila had accepted an offer from Emperor
Theodosius II, the Eastern Roman Emperor
throughout virtually the entire first half of the
fifth century AD, to become an uneasy ally of the
Romans, in return for not attacking their lands
to the south and Rugila was given the honorary
title of a general in the Roman military. More
importantly, he was paid an annual tribute of
350 pounds of gold to protect the northern border
of the Eastern Roman Empire. Given that the Hun
confederacy was the primary threat to the empire’s
border at this time, the tribute was effectively
extortion money exacted from the imperial
government in return for not attacking the empire.
The question for Attila and Bleda when they
rose to power in around 434 AD, was whether
they would continue to simply exact tributes from
the Romans in return for passively residing in the
Carpathian Basin, or if they would resume their
destructive attacks to the south.
The empire that Attila and Bleda were succeeding
to as joint rulers, was considerable. The Huns
controlled a large expanse of territory,
stretching from around the banks of the River
Rhine in the west, to the Pontic-Caspian Steppe in
the east around modern-day Ukraine. This included
the northern parts of the Balkans, meaning
that they had extended their sphere of control
to the edge of the Western Roman Empire and were
occupying the northern parts of the Eastern Roman
Empire. The centre of this territorial empire
was most likely in the Carpathian Basin, a
large flatland which lies primarily in modern-day
Hungary and which is surrounded by the Carpathian
Mountains, the Balkan Mountains and the Dinaric
Alps. The flatlands here were an ideal place
for the Huns to establish themselves, as they
were pastoralists, who rode horses into battle,
lived primarily off livestock, and were used to
living on large flat expanses like this on the
Pontic-Caspian and Asian Steppes. Thus, although
we cannot be certain exactly where the centre
of power of the Hun empire was, most studies
favour the idea that Attila and Bleda would have
operated from the Carpathian Basin. This was not
a territorial state in the modern sense or even in
the way that the Romans exercised power. It was
more of a sphere of influence throughout which,
the Huns exacted tribute. Moreover, although
they were effectively occupying lands which
had traditionally been part of the Roman Empire,
the governments of neither the Eastern or Western
empires were in a position to try to expel them
from these lands in the 430s or 440s AD.
The ethnic composition of the empire of the Huns
and of their armies was complex. In the studies
of the so-called ‘barbarian migrations’ that were
written for much of the twentieth century, various
Germanic and Asiatic groups that invaded the Roman
Empire between the third and fifth centuries AD,
were generally depicted as being homogenous
ethnic groups. Today it is recognised that the
armies that invaded the Roman Empire were much
more ethnically varied. While the Huns were the
dominant group within their numbers, their armies
and their empire were more of a confederation of
Germanic and Asiatic groups that were allied
together against the Romans. These included
the remnants of the Goths in the Balkans and
additional groups that had been attacking the
Roman borders for centuries, notably the Alans
and Sarmatians, while people such as the Sciri
and Heruls were also involved. Hence, Attila
was not the ruler of a unitary Hunnic state,
but rather he and Bleda had ascended
to control a confederation of nomadic,
warrior people drawn to Rome’s borders by the
promise of rich plunder for those willing to
attack the declining empire.
Attila and Bleda did not change the strategy which
Rugila had adopted in the Balkans years earlier.
They renegotiated the terms of the tribute with
Emperor Theodosius II to receive a larger amount
of tribute and also to increase the amount of
trade between the Huns and the Romans, but the
broad deal remained in place for several years
after the two brothers ascended to lead the
Hun confederacy. Instead, the Huns and their
other Germanic and Asiatic allies went east and
descended into the Caucasus to campaign against
the northern borders of the Sassanid Persian
empire, a move which the Eastern Roman government
in Constantinople, the longstanding adversary of
the Persians, were undoubtedly happy about. This
campaign was not as successful for the Huns
as earlier ones in Europe, perhaps because
of the sheer distance from their main base of
operations in the Carpathian Basin. Therefore,
around 440 AD, Attila and Bleda reorientated
their strategy again and began attacking the
Eastern Roman Empire. In 441 AD they flattened the
town of Margus near the Danube River, apparently
under the simple pretext that the local Christian
bishop had offended the sensibilities of the Huns,
who adhered to a religion with elements of
polytheism and animism. The years that followed
saw sporadic clashes in the northern Balkans as
Theodosius’ government fluctuated between trying
to militarily challenge the Huns and simply
paying them off with ever larger tributes.
This changing strategy was determined in part
by events elsewhere as Emperor Theodosius tried
to move legions from North Africa and the Levant
to the Balkans. By 443 and 444 AD, the conflict
was intensifying as it became apparent that
Theodosius intended to resist the Huns.
The war between the Huns and the Eastern Roman
Empire would reach its peak in the second half of
the 440s AD. By then Attila was the sole ruler
of the Huns. Bleda died around 445 AD. It is
usually stated as a fact that Attila killed his
own brother in order to concentrate power in his
own hands. However, there is actually very little
evidence regarding Bleda’s demise. For instance,
Jordanes stated that “when his brother Bleda,
who ruled over a great part of the Huns,
had been slain by his treachery, Attila united
all the people under his own rule.” Later medieval
accounts such as the Chronicon Pictum, written
by Mark of Kalt in the fourteenth century,
embellished on this and stated that “Attila went
in the city of Sicambria in Pannonia, where he
killed Bleda, his brother, and he threw his corpse
into the Danube.” There really is no evidence to
support this. The story of Attila’s murder of
his own brother became more elaborate over time,
yet in reality, the evidence of the ancient
sources only implies that Attila had his brother
killed in order to claim complete power himself.
There isn’t much evidence, though, to say how,
where, when and why this happened. What is
beyond doubt is that Attila entered into the most
dangerous phase of his career after Bleda’s death.
In 447 AD the Huns burst through the borders
of the Eastern Roman Empire and devastated the
provinces covering modern-day Serbia and Bulgaria.
They won a major victory at the Battle of Utus and
threatened the capital, but Constantinople’s great
walls were too formidable to penetrate. Instead,
Theodosius decided to once again bribe Attila,
this time paying him an enormous tribute
of over 2,000 pounds of gold.
The organisation of peace between the Eastern
Roman Empire and the Huns in the aftermath of the
Battle of Utus saw Priscus, our leading source for
Attila’s actions in the Balkans, visit the Hunnic
court as part of the diplomatic negotiations. This
was fortunate, as Priscus afterwards left behind
a detailed description of what he saw there.
This clearly indicates that the court of the
nomadic Huns was not stationary. It moved around
and was made from wooden structures that could
be taken apart, transported and reassembled. For
instance, Priscus noted that “Attila’s residence,
which was situated here, was said to be more
splendid than his houses in other places.
It was made of polished boards, and surrounded
with wooden enclosures, designed not so much for
protection as for appearance’ sake.” Nevertheless,
while they might have been moving around, and been
a warlike people, Priscus indicates that the Huns
had adopted some of the luxuries of life in the
Roman Empire. For instance, he noted that Attila’s
second-in-command, a chieftain named Onegesius,
had a bath-house next to his house. Elsewhere
Priscus observed “buildings of carved boards
beautifully fitted together, others of straight
planed beams, without carving, fastened on round
wooden blocks which rose to a moderate height
from the ground,” while inside these buildings
were furnished with couches and woollen
mats. This was not a primitive setting.
Priscus went on to provide an account of his
direct encounter with the leader of the Huns
and his observations of how the royal court
functioned: “He came forth from the house
with a dignified strut, looking round on this side
and on that. He was accompanied by Onegesius, and
stood in front of the house; and many persons who
had lawsuits with one another came up and received
his judgment. Then he returned into the house and
received ambassadors of barbarous peoples.” What
is most striking about this is that the Roman
embassies from both the Western and Eastern
empires were made to wait to be called one by one
to come before Attila: “When the hour arrived we
went to the palace, along with the embassy from
the western Romans, and stood on the threshold of
the hall in the presence of Attila. The cupbearers
gave us a cup, according to the national custom,
that we might pray before we sat down. Having
tasted the cup, we proceeded to take our seats,
all the chairs being ranged along the walls of
the room on either side. Attila sat in the middle
on a couch; a second couch was set behind
him, and from it steps led up to his bed,
which was covered with linen sheets and wrought
coverlets for ornament, such as Greeks and Romans
used to deck bridal beds.” As the evening went
on a feast began. This was not rustic. Fine food
was brought in on silver platters, but Priscus
noted that Attila was content with more simple
fare served in a simple way: “Attila ate nothing
but meat on a wooden trencher. In everything else,
too, he showed himself temperate — his cup was
of wood, while to the guests were given goblets
of gold and silver. His dress, too, was quite
simple, affecting only to be clean. The sword he
carried at his side, the ratchets of his Scythian
shoes, the bridle of his horse were not adorned,
like those of the other Scythians, with gold or
gems or anything costly.” The only affectation
here by the leader of the Huns was after the meal,
when “evening fell and torches were lit, and two
barbarians coming forward in front of Attila
sang songs they had composed, celebrating his
victories and deeds of valour in war.”
When Priscus departed from the court of Attila
the Hun, the warlord was about to embark
on a new strategy. Heretofore the Huns had
primarily focused on attacking the Eastern
Roman Empire, but with peace established in
447 AD with the government of Emperor Theodosius
II in Constantinople, Attila looked westwards.
The Western Roman Empire had been under the
rule of Emperor Valentinian III since 425 AD,
though he had succeeded to the imperial title
when he was a six-year old child and only began
to rule himself in the 440s AD. During his
younger years, the situation in the empire
had gone from bad to worse. Already at the time
of his accession, Britain had been abandoned and
groups like the Franks, Visigoths and Vandals
occupied large parts of Gaul and Hispania.
Things became worse still in 429 AD when the
new ruler of the Vandals in Hispania, Gaiseric,
assembled a large fleet and led tens of thousands
of his followers across the Mediterranean to North
Africa. Over the next ten years the Vandals carved
out their own kingdom in North Africa, stretching
all the way from the Straits of Gibraltar to the
city of Carthage in modern-day Tunisia, ending the
rule of the Western Roman Empire here. Therefore,
when Valentinian came of age in the 440s AD, the
western empire was broadly confined to controlling
Italy and parts of southern and eastern Gaul.
They still aspired to control northern and
western Gaul, parts of Germania and even Hispania,
but the Visigoths, Franks and Burgundians were
more influential in these regions and only gave
allegiance to the Romans intermittently. It
was against this decaying power that Attila
turned his forces in the late 440s AD.
He would face a formidable adversary in Western
Europe, though it was not the Emperor Valentinian
III. This was Flavius Aetius. He was born in the
Balkans in the late fourth century, though he was
descended from the old Roman aristocracy of Italy
on his mother’s side. As a teenager he had been a
hostage in the entourage of Alaric the Goth as he
rampaged through Italy in the period prior to the
sack of Rome in 410 AD. Later Aetius spent time
at the court of the Huns in the Balkans during
the era when Uldin and Charaton were the rulers
of the Hun confederacy. Therefore, the figure
who would lead the defence of the Western Roman
Empire against Attila’s assault in the late
440s and early 450s AD was very familiar with
the Huns and their confederates in the Balkans.
He was also a very experienced general. Aetius
had campaigned extensively against the Franks and
Visigoths in Gaul from the late 420s AD onwards.
He had been comparatively successful in trying
to re-establish Roman control over the region
north from the Alps along the Rhone River towards
the western bank of the Rhine, the old northern
frontier of the empire. However, after Valentinian
III came of age, clashes between the emperor and
the general began. Thus, not only was the Western
Roman Empire being viciously attacked by Germanic
groups like the Vandals, Visigoths and Franks that
were living within Gaul, Hispania and North Africa
but there was also an internal power struggle
between the Emperor Valentinian III and the most
powerful general of the era, Aetius.
Attila’s decision to campaign westwards was
seemingly inspired by the sister of Emperor
Valentinian III, a woman named Honoria. Polygamy
was practised by the Huns and Attila had multiple
wives or concubines and many children already.
Still, he determined after establishing peace
terms with the Eastern Roman Empire that he would
campaign west and marry Honoria. Remarkably,
she appears to have established contact with
Attila and had requested that he come to Italy.
The backstory was unusual. Honoria was pregnant
from a relationship with a court functionary
and her brother had placed her under a de-facto
house arrest when he discovered that she was
with child. Honoria had consequently requested
Attila to come to rescue her, an invitation which
the Hun leader interpreted as a call for him to
come to Italy and claim her hand in marriage.
While he was interpreting this overture in
a self-serving manner, he also conveniently
decided to conclude that Honoria’s dowry or
marriage portion would be half of the remaining
territories of the Western Roman Empire. Thus,
at the end of the 440s AD Attila led a large army
west to claim these lands and rescue his future
bride. Ancient sources typically exaggerated
the size of barbarian armies and this was no
exception. They proposed that the Huns and their
allies numbered upwards of half a million men who
streamed over the Rhine into Gaul to try to
conquer the remaining Roman lands there. The
likelihood is that Attila led tens of thousands
of men into the lands of the Western Roman Empire,
but nowhere near the hundreds of thousands that
were suggested in the ancient accounts.
Attila’s initial aim was to seize control of the
Roman lands on the west side of the Rhine and
into Gaul around what we know today as Belgium
and north-eastern France. Aetius moved north to
stop him, gathering allies amongst the Franks and
Visigoths who understandably believed that they
had to make common cause with the Romans to avoid
being displaced by the Huns themselves. Meanwhile,
the Christian bishops of northern Gaul tried
to organise the immediate defence of the cities
and towns here. Some reached accommodations with
Attila to avoid the Huns plundering their cities,
others tried to resist. It was while describing
this invasion that the Latin term Flagellum Dei,
‘the scourge of god’, was first used to describe
Attila. The Hun army that campaigned into Gaul
would have closely resembled a description
given in the late fourth century AD by the
Roman military commander and historian, Ammianus
Marcellinus. He had described them as having no
regular battle order. Instead “they move quickly
and suddenly, now dispersing, now coming together
over the ramparts and pillaging the camp
before their approach had become known.”
He also described them using nets that they
threw over enemy soldiers from their horses
before closing to massacre them.
The one thing they could not do was penetrate
large city walls, as they were not skilled at
siege warfare. Thus, the city of Orleans in
northern Gaul was able to withstand an attack
by them. Not long after abandoning his attack
on this city, Attila finally clashed with the army
Aetius had gathered at Chalons. The Battle of the
Catalaunian Fields, as it is known, was fought on
the 19th of September 451 AD. With perhaps a touch
of hyperbole, Jordanes later claimed that during
it “the fighting became hand-to-hand, fierce,
savage, confused and without the slightest
respite. No ancient saga has recorded such
a conflict … Our elders report that the blood from
the bodies of the slain turned a small brook which
flowed through the plain into a gushing river.” At
the end of it, Attila and his confederate forces
fell back and retreated, though this was not an
unequivocal victory for the Romans. Although we
can dismiss the claim made by the historian
Hydatius that 300,000 men died in the clash,
both sides suffered heavy losses, most notably
the Roman’s Visigothic allies, whose king,
Theodoric, was slain in the battle. Aetius chose
not to follow up his victory by chasing Attila
towards the Rhine. In reality he was not at
liberty to do so. A large contingent of the
so-called ‘Roman’ army at Chalons was made up
of Germanic allies and with their king dead,
the Visigoths entered into a civil war between
his sons, Theodoric and Thorismund.
Attila and his forces retreated back east of the
Rhine into Germania and wintered there. He would
not trouble Gaul ever again. Instead he now turned
his attentions southwards towards Italy itself,
perhaps aware that Aetius and the Emperor
Valentinian III were not aligned on any
real level, while also realising that the
stout defence he had run into in Gaul was
largely comprised of the Visigoths and Franks,
whereas he would encounter less resistance if
he struck south of the Alps. He also possibly
wanted to emulate Alaric the Goth’s capture of
the city of Rome back in 410 AD. Thus, in 452 AD
Attila led his forces south into Italy. Strangely,
though, this campaign was aborted after he
met with Pope Leo near the Mincius River
in northern Italy. We have an account of
this in Prosper of Aquitaine’s chronicle.
He states, “Attila, having once more collected
his forces which had been scattered in Gaul,
took his way through Pannonia into Italy … to the
emperor and the senate, and to the Roman people,
none of all the proposed plans to oppose the
enemy seemed so practicable to send the legates
to the most savage king to beg for peace. Our most
blessed Pope Leo – trusting to the help of God,
who never fails the righteous in their trials
– undertook the task … the outcome was what his
faith had foreseen, for when the king had received
the embassy, he was so impressed by the presence
of the high priest that he ordered his army to
give up warfare, and after he had promised peace,
he departed beyond the Danube.” Hence, in 451
AD Attila was rebuffed in his invasion of Gaul,
while a year later he was convinced by Pope Leo to
call off his invasion of Italy.
Undoubtedly the descriptions of Attila and Leo’s
meeting were written with a Christian bias. One
version even has St Peter and St Paul appearing to
help Leo convince Attila to abandon his campaign.
The likelihood is that Attila had invaded northern
Italy to try to restore his reputation and pride
after the defeat in Gaul the previous autumn, and
after plundering the towns of northern Italy he
abandoned the campaign under the pretext
of having reached an agreement with Leo.
He might have also realised after travelling
through Germania, northern Gaul and northern
Italy that the Huns were better off attacking the
much wealthier Eastern Roman Empire after all,
rather than the poor husk of what remained
of the Western Roman Empire. Hence,
after his meeting with Leo, Attila led his
men back to the Carpathian Basin and began
preparing for a fresh campaign in the Balkans.
A new emperor named Marcian had ascended to
rule over the Eastern Roman Empire after the
nearly half-century long rule of Theodosius
II. He had even launched a campaign into
the Hun territories in 452 AD while Attila
was distracted in Western Europe. Therefore,
Attila was set on shoring up his position in the
Balkans as he moved back eastwards. The intended
campaign would never take place though.
Attila was still only in his late forties
at this time, perhaps nearing his fiftieth
year. He could have continued to plague the
Romans in both the west and east for many
years more had his life not been cut short under
suspicious circumstances. Whether he was poisoned
or died by some alternative form of treachery
remains a point of debate amongst historians.
The most detailed account of his death comes
from Jordanes, who quotes Priscus. Jordanes
tells us that shortly before he died, Attila
married a certain Ildico, possibly the daughter
of one of his Germanic allies based on her name.
She was one of several wives. The wedding feast
was the occasion of his death. Jordanes states
that “He had given himself up to excessive joy
at his wedding, and as he lay on his back, heavy
with wine and sleep, a rush of superfluous blood,
which would ordinarily have flowed from his
nose, streamed in deadly course down his throat
and killed him, since it was hindered in the usual
passages. Thus, did drunkenness put a disgraceful
end to a king renowned in war. On the following
day, when a great part of the morning was spent,
the royal attendants suspected some ill and,
after a great uproar, broke in the doors. There
they found the death of Attila accomplished
by an effusion of blood, without any wound,
and Ildico with downcast face weeping beneath
her veil. Then, as is the custom of that race,
they plucked out the hair of their heads and
made their faces hideous with deep wounds,
that the renowned warrior might be mourned, not
by effeminate wailings and tears, but by the blood
of men.” Perhaps it was a haemorrhage of some
kind brought on by excessive drinking, though
some historians believe based on this account that
Attila was poisoned in the course of the wedding
feast and died during the night.
News of Attila’s death went out across Europe.
Indeed, Jordanes claims that the event was so
momentous that Emperor Marcian had a vision
from god alerting him to the passing of the
Romans’ greatest nemesis, “for so terrible was
Attila thought to be to great empires that the
gods announced his death to rulers as a special
boon.” In the aftermath of his suspicious death,
several of Attila’s sons attempted to take his
place. These were Ellac, Ernak and Dengizich.
A division of power between them would not have
been out of the ordinary, as Attila and Bleda had
been joint rulers of the confederacy for a decade
before Bleda’s death. However, Attila’s sons
immediately tried to claim power for themselves
and tore the Hun confederacy apart in the process.
In the vacuum that was created, one of Attila’s
former commanders, a man named Ardaric, who was
a member of the Gepids, a Germanic tribe that
formed part of the Hun confederacy, seized
power after defeating Attila’s sons at the
Battle of Nedao in 454 AD. He established
a new confederacy under Gepid leadership,
one which was ultimately more enduring that that
of the Huns. For instance, a Gepid ruler named
Mundo or Mundus was still an important individual
amongst the Germanic tribes in the Carpathian
Basin three-quarters of a century later. He
is believed to have been Ardaric’s grandson.
These developments once again suggest that
the empire of Attila the Hun was really just
a confederacy of Germanic and Asiatic tribes
based out of the Carpathian Basin in which the
Huns were briefly the pre-eminent group between
the early fifth century and the time of Attila’s
death. After his passing and the overthrow of
his sons, the Huns faded away as a power and
were replaced by newcomers like the Gepids.
As transient as the Hun confederacy had been,
its timing was significant. The Eastern Roman
Empire recovered in the medium term and entered
back into a period of rejuvenation in the
sixth century. During the long reign of the
Emperor Justinian between 527 AD and 565 AD, the
Eastern Empire even managed to re-conquer parts
of the Western Mediterranean around modern-day
Tunisia, Catalonia, Sicily and southern Italy,
although the rise of Islam and the Arab Conquests
of the seventh century, combined with new waves of
Slavic invaders from Asia into the Balkans
reduced the Eastern Empire to a rump state
hundreds of years later. The impact of the Huns on
the Western Roman Empire was more dramatic. Only
23 years after the death of Attila the Hun, the
last Western Roman Emperor, Romulus Augustulus,
was deposed by a Germanic warlord named Odoacer.
This event in 476 AD is seen as marking the end
of the Western Roman Empire. In medieval
times the view consequently emerged that
Attila’s campaigns into Italy and other parts of
Western Europe had fatally weakened the Western
Empire and paved the way for its termination 23
years after his death. This interpretation had
extra credence given that only two years after
Attila’s death, the Vandals had crossed to Italy
from North Africa and became the second Germanic
group in less than half a century to sack Rome
when they did so in 455 AD.
It was owing to the belief that Attila had
fatally weakened the Western Roman Empire and
paved the way for the Vandal assault and the
deposition of Romulus Augustulus that Attila
later became known as the major figure in the
fall of the Western Roman Empire. Elaborate
myths concerning Attila developed as well.
One held that he had possessed the sword of Mars,
the Roman god of war. Elements of his life story
were even transmitted north to Scandinavia and
were incorporated into Norse myths that were
written down in the High Middle Ages 700 to 800
years after Attila’s own time. He was central
to the Middle High German poem, ‘The Song of the
Nibelungs’, while Ludwig von Beethoven considered
writing an opera about Attila and he featured
in numerous paintings produced in the nineteenth
century. There is no obvious reason why Attila
acquired such a position of infamy when he never
sacked Rome like Alaric the Goth had, nor did
he conquer entire provinces the way the Vandals
had in North Africa. Nevertheless, the myth of
Attila grew and grew over the centuries.
Attila the Hun’s name has become a byword for
the violent invasion of the Roman Empire which
brought the western half of the empire to an
end in the fifth century AD. He holds a place
in the western imagination similar to that
of Genghis Khan as an Asiatic warlord whose
forces were virtually invincible. The reality
is actually quite different. Almost nothing is
known about his background and early life, though
he clearly came from a family that was involved
in the leadership of the Hun confederacy in the
early fifth century. In the mid-430s AD, he and
his brother Bleda became the new leaders, though
Attila appears to have eventually orchestrated the
murder of his brother and became sole ruler of the
confederacy in the mid-440s AD. This being said,
it is important to remember that the Huns were not
a homogenous group that threatened the Western and
Eastern Roman Empire for decades. They were the
foremost group amongst a confederacy of Germanic
and Asiatic tribes based out of the Carpathian
Basin. There is no doubt that Attila plagued
both the Eastern and Western halves of the empire,
but this needs to be viewed in context. While the
Eastern Roman Empire still had some vitality to it
and would rebound strongly from its difficulties
in the sixth century, the Western Roman Empire
was in its death throes already by the time Attila
became leader of the Hun confederacy. Rome had
been sacked in 410 AD and groups like the Angles,
Saxons, Franks, Visigoths and Vandals had
already overrun most of it. Attila clearly
weakened it further and left an impression
on contemporaries and medieval chroniclers,
but he was just one of several prominent Germanic
and Asiatic leaders who brought the Roman Empire
to the verge of ruin in the fourth and fifth
centuries. It is arguable that Alaric the Goth,
the warlord who sacked Rome in 410 AD, or
Gaiseric, the Vandal king who conquered North
Africa and then sacked Rome for a second time in
455 AD, were far more consequential in the fall
of the Western Roman Empire. Nonetheless, it was
Attila who has become the paragon of the barbarian
warlord who destroyed the Western Roman Empire and
plunged Western Europe into the Dark Ages.
What do you think of Attila the Hun? Was he really
the most powerful adversary the Romans faced in
late antiquity, or has his status as the so-called
‘scourge of god’ been strangely overstated?
Please let us know in the comment section, and in
the meantime, thank you very much for watching.